Mr.
Speaker 1: President, I stood before this body in March of this year to protest our country's unconstitutional intervention in Saudi Arabia's bloody war
in Yemen.
Speaker 1: I was proud to stand with my colleagues, Senator Sanders and Senator Murphy, to file a discharge motion of our resolution, S.J. Res. 54, that
would remove
Speaker 1: U.S. Armed Forces from
Yemen.
At that
Speaker 2: time, members of the Foreign Relations Committee requested additional time to study the issue and to debate the resolution in the Foreign Relations Committee. The chairman of that committee,
Speaker 3: my friend and colleague from Tennessee, Senator
Corker,
Speaker 1: requested this with the commitment to, quote, bring forth legislation to actually appropriately deal with many of the issues relative to Yemen, Saudi Arabia, and ourselves.
Speaker 1: Close quote.
So
Speaker 4: with that, the Senate voted to table the motion. Now, since then, the committee has held a hearing on this issue and introduced a separate bipartisan bill to address it. But no further action has been taken. And so today,
Speaker 5: eight months later, the bloodshed continues, still abetted by the United States, even amidst further revelations of
Speaker 2: Saudi depravity.
It is
Speaker 2: long past overdue that Congress remove US forces from Yemen, as recent circumstances only confirm. Today, we
Speaker 4: have the chance to remedy our course of action
Speaker 5: and to do what the Constitution and justice demand. The
Speaker 4: situation in Yemen
is dire.
Speaker 4: The war has killed tens of thousands of innocent civilians, human beings lest we forget,
Speaker 1: each one of them possessing immeasurable dignity and inherent worth. It has created refugees,
Speaker 2: orphans, widows, and it's also displaced countless families. The
Speaker 5: numbers and the inhumanity are staggering, nothing short of it. Since 2015, more than 10,000 civilians have died, and 40,000 have been wounded.
In an
Speaker 5: attack just a few months ago, a bomb was dropped on a school bus that killed 40 young boys who were on a school trip and wounded another
Speaker 1: children. But what few Americans knew until recently is that the U.S. military has actually
Speaker 5: been making the crisis worse by helping one side bomb these innocent civilians.
How
Speaker 5: did we get entangled in this crisis to begin with? Well in March of 2015,
Speaker 4: Saudi Arabia launched a war against the Houthi rebels shortly after the Houthis ousted the Saudi-backed government in the capital city
of Sana'a.
Speaker 4: The Obama administration, without consulting Congress,
quickly
Speaker 5: authorized U.S. military forces to provide logistical and intelligence support to the Saudi-led coalition.
Speaker 1: U.S. military support has continued since then, including mid-air refueling,
Speaker 3: surveillance, reconnaissance information, and target selection assistance. In other words, we've been supporting and actively participating in the activities of war in Yemen. But
Article I, Section 8 of
Speaker 5: the Constitution states that Congress shall have the power to declare war. Congress.
Not
Speaker 5: the president, not the Pentagon, not someone else in the executive branch. Not any other part of government, but Congress. The founders could not have been any clearer about this. And they did so,
Mr.
Speaker 4: President, with very good reason. The founders set up our system of government in such a way as to protect the people from the dangers associated with the excessive accumulation of power in the
Speaker 3: hands of the few.
We know
Speaker 3: from
Speaker 5: experience,
and we
Speaker 5: knew then from our young nation's experience under British rule that bad things happen, especially at a national level, when too few people exercise too much power and that power goes unchecked. And nowhere is this more evident than in the case of the power to declare war. So the founders placed that power squarely in the legislative branch.
The
Speaker 5: branch where honest, open, and public debate is supposed to happen,
and the
Speaker 5: branch that is held most accountable to the people through elections,
at the
Speaker 5: most regular intervals. As Alexander Hamilton pointed out in Federalist's paper number
Speaker 4: 69, this power would not be exercised by the executive branch so that it would be less likely to be
Speaker 5: abused, just like it was when the King of England acted...
in and of
Speaker 5: himself, by himself, to send his country, and ours for that matter,
into war.
Speaker 5: Now, some opponents of our resolution claim that our involvement in Yemen is somehow constitutionally justified under the War Powers
Speaker 6: Act
of 1973.
Speaker 7: This isn't true. Now, it is true that the War Powers
Act
Speaker 2: makes it possible for the executive branch of government acting alone to use armed forces in cases of emergencies
Speaker 5: and subject to certain limited defined time constraints. But the conflict in Yemen by no means, in no way, shape,
or form
Speaker 5: constitutes a threat to the safety of American citizens. And our involvement has far surpassed the allotted emergency time constraint. The Houthis,
Speaker 5: Well, no friends of ours are a regional rebel group, one that does not itself threaten American national security. In fact, the longer we fight against them, the more reason we give them to hate America and embrace the opportunists who are our true enemy in the region are wrong.
The
Speaker 3: more we prolong the activities that destabilize the region, the longer we harm our own interests in terms of trade,
and
Speaker 3: broader
Speaker 4: regional security.
The War
Speaker 4: Powers Act also states that the assignment of U.S. armed forces to coordinate or participate in hostilities of a foreign country constitutes a conflict of war.
And some
Speaker 4: have argued that we have
Speaker 5: not been engaging in hostilities
and
Speaker 8: therefore have not violated the War Powers
Act.
But
Speaker 8: this claim, too, falls flat on its face. We've
Speaker 5: specifically aided the Saudi coalition with mid-air refueling and target selection assistance. Or, as Defense Secretary Jim Mattis himself said in December of 2017, our military is helping the Saudis "make certain they hit
Speaker 8: the right thing." In other words, we're helping a foreign power bomb its adversaries.
Speaker 8: If that doesn't constitute hostilities, I don't know what
does.
Speaker 2: Now, finally, some critics say that this resolution would somehow hurt our efforts to combat terrorism in the region, specifically
Speaker 3: al-Qaeda and ISIS. However, the resolution explicitly states that it would not impede
the
Speaker 5: military's ability to fight these terror groups. In fact, U.S. involvement in Yemen
has
Speaker 5: arguably undermined the effort against al-Qaeda's affiliates. The State
Speaker 4: Department's country reports on terrorism for 2016 found that the conflict between the Saudi-led forces and the Houthi insurgents has actually helped al-Qaeda in the Arabian
Speaker 5: Peninsula and ISIS's Yemen branch to deepen their inroads across much of
the country.
Speaker 5: It appears that our involvement in Yemen accomplishes no good at
all.
Speaker 5: only harm, and serious consequential harm at that.
The situation
Speaker 5: in Yemen now poses
Speaker 1: a true humanitarian crisis.
The country is
Speaker 1: on the brink of rampant disease and mass starvation. An estimated 15
Speaker 5: million people don't have access to clean water and sanitation, and 17 million don't have access to food.
More innocent
Speaker 5: lives,
are
Speaker 4: being lost every single day. My position on this has not changed for
the past
Speaker 4: eight months. But
with the
Speaker 4: taking of another
Speaker 5: innocent life, that of Jamal Khashoggi, the circumstances have only further deteriorated. Intelligence suggests, despite his repeated denials, that the Crown Prince of
Speaker 9: Saudi Arabia himself
Speaker 4: ordered the murder. Saudi Arabia's moral depravity
has
Speaker 4: only been made plainer.
This is
Speaker 4: not an ally that deserves our support or military intervention on its behalf, especially when
Speaker 5: our own security is not itself on the line. On the contrary, to continue supporting them in this war would be bad diplomacy and undermine our very credibility.
No, U.S.
Speaker 5: intervention in Yemen is unauthorized, unconstitutional,
Speaker 5: and immoral. And we must not, we cannot delay voting to end our involvement
Speaker 4: and our support of Saudi Arabia any further. If we do,
we have
Speaker 4: ourselves to blame for our country's lost credibility on the world
stage. And
Speaker 4: more importantly, our own consciences will bear the blame for the thousands of lives that will surely continue
Speaker 2: to be
lost.
The
Speaker 2: Founding Fathers had incredible wisdom in requiring these issues, issues of American blood and American treasure, to be debated and discussed
Speaker 5: between two equal branches of government. They understood that matters of war and alliances must constantly be reconsidered and reevaluated and in an open, honest,
Speaker 4: and public manner. That is one of our most solemn duties in this
body.
And
Speaker 4: it's the opportunity that lies squarely before us today. We
owe it to the
Speaker 4: sons and daughters of the American people who put their sons and daughters in harm's way to defend us. We owe it to their parents
Speaker 5: and their families. We owe it to ourselves,
who have
Speaker 5: taken an oath to uphold, protect, and
Speaker 10: defend the Constitution of the United States.
I urge
Speaker 10: my colleagues to vote in favor of the motion to discharge your resolution.
Thank you, Mr.
Speaker 10: President. I yield the floor.